When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
Bear in mind, they only struggle to form connections.
不过需要注意的是 这些人只是不擅长社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来
-WOW! -STARTLE!
（惊吓 欢呼）
NAJIMI'S REACTION
（驯染的反应）
Oh, Komi!
古见同学
Love it!
不错哦！
SPARKLE
（闪亮）
YAMAI'S REACTION
（山井同学的反应）
Good morning, Komi!
早安 古见同学！
TWITCH
（痉挛）
-AGARI'S REACTION -JIGGLE
（上理同学的反应 软绵绵）
TADANO'S REACTION
（只野同学的反应）
Good morning, Komi!
早安 古见同学！
EVERYONE'S ACTING DIFFERENT. DO I LOOK WEIRD?
（大家的反应和平常不太一样 我是不是有哪里怪怪的？）
No, you look good.
我觉得很好看
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
This has been the reaction to Komi's summer uniform.
以上是大家对古见同学 夏季制服的反应
MISSION 13 "IT'S JUST A FITNESS TEST."
（任务13 体能测验）
Hey! So we meet again! It's Makeru Yadano!
嗨 我们又见面了 我是矢田野真华留！
Last time, the physical exam ended in a tie.
上次健康检查打成平手
But thanks to that, Komi and I are now serious rivals, right?
但大家因此也明白了 我和古见同学是势均力敌的对手吧？
Right?
对吧？
Alright, today is the fitness test! It's on, Komi!
好 这次要比体能测验 我们分个高下吧 古见同学！
Ow!
好痛！
It's Komi in gym clothes with a ponytail!
古见同学穿运动服 还绑马尾！
YADANO HATES TO LOSE
（矢田野同学很不服输）
PHYSICAL EXAM SEVEN ROUNDS
（体能测验七局赛）
GRIP STRENGTH KOMI: 24KG / YADANO: 18KG
（握力 古见24公斤 矢田野18公斤）
SIT AND REACH KOMI: 52CM / YADANO: 45CM
（体前屈 古见52厘米 矢田野45厘米）
SIDE STEP KOMI: 48 / YADANO: 42
（反复侧步跳 古见48次 矢田野42次）
SIT-UPS KOMI: 22 / YADANO: 21
（仰卧起坐 古见22 矢田野21）
So close!
好可惜！
LONG JUMP KOMI: 203CM / YADANO: 165CM
（立定跳远 古见203厘米 矢田野165厘米）
HANDBALL THROW KOMI: 26M / YADANO: 1M
（手球掷远 古见26米 矢田野1米）
I lost at everything.
全都输了
Huh?
奇怪
Yadano, what's wrong? Not feeling well?
矢田野 你怎么了？身体不舒服吗？
I hate this!
我不甘心！
50M RUN
（50米赛跑）
This is the last test.
这是最后一个项目
If I can't win this, it'll be 7-0.
如果不拿下这一局 我就是零胜
A total defeat.
那就是全面败北
I think fate is something you can change.
我认为人生是可以靠自己来改变的
Without being influenced by talent or DNA.
不会受到出身、天赋以及DNA的影响
On your marks.
各就各位
If you work hard, you can become who you want to be.
只要努力 就能成为理想中的自己
Ready.
预备
In order to prove this,
为了证明这一点
I…
我…
must win!
非赢不可！
No matter the cost!
不惜付出任何代价！
I'm pretty fast! My legs never let me down!
怎么样？很快吧？ 我对自己的脚程是很有信心的！
Never mind my looks!
我完全豁出去了！
Who cares about femininity and cuteness?
顾不上女人味跟可爱的外表了！
I just want one thing where I'm better than Komi!
我只要赢过古见同学一个项目就好！
Beautiful…
好美
KOMI: 6.89 SEC
（古见同学 6秒89）
Um, you got 6.89.
我看看 你跑了6秒89
Yeah, right there.
对 写那里
Komi.
古见同学
Watching you run made me realize how far I've strayed from the true path.
看到你跑步的样子 让我明白了自己的内心是多么丑恶
You win this time.
这场比赛是我输了
Thanks for the challenge.
谢谢你愿意跟我比赛
GLISTEN
（闪亮）
DOESN'T RECALL ISSUING A CHALLENGE
（对此事完全没印象）
You won't shake my hand.
你不肯跟我握手啊
Ah, it's a sign I've given up.
握手其实代表着我放弃了
You want to tell me to keep working at it.
所以你希望我继续努力对吧？
In other words, you accept me as your rival!
也就是说你承认了我是你的劲敌！
I won't lose next time, Komi!
下次我不会输给你的 古见同学！
Our battle has just begun!
我们俩的战斗才刚开始呢！
Komi earned herself a rival.
古见同学得到了一名劲敌
I mean, buying fast food only takes like five minutes, right?
话说买快餐大概要花五分钟吧？
So I thought it would be okay.
所以我想只停一下应该没关系
But the bike parking patrol guy was right there.
结果碰到严格取缔 违规停自行车的大叔
You know what he said to me?
那个大叔这样跟我说
"You"…
“你啊…”
Oh, hey Komi, can we come over today?
啊 古见同学 今天可以去你家玩吗？
Huh? I want to hear what happened next.
什么？好想知道刚才那件事的后续
To her house?
你想去她家玩？
Isn't that kind of ambitious Naji--
这难度会不会太高了点？驯…
Komi is conflicted!
古见同学在纠结！
She has always wanted to have friends over.
她内心向往着邀请朋友到家里玩
Yet she's embarrassed to show her home life.
但又同时羞于将私生活示人
Plus so many other anxiety-causing elements.
加上其他不安要素 她内心一定无比纠结吧！
I understand, Komi!
我懂 古见同学 我懂！
What's up with this mind-reading power?
你的读心能力从哪儿来的？
NOD
（点头）
Really?
可以吗？
Which is it?
到底可不可以啊？
Wow, what a lovely house!
好气派的独栋住宅！
-Thanks for having us! -ZERO HESITATION.
-那我就打扰喽！ -（毫不犹豫）
Hang on…
等等…
Hello!
你好！
She's so pretty!
大美女！
That intimidating aura!
这个强大的气场！
-Those eyes. -That nose.
-那双眼睛 -那个鼻子
That's definitely Komi's mom!
她肯定是古见同学的妈妈！
What, no way! Shoko's friends?
天啊 是硝子的朋友吗？
It's the first time ever!
这可是她第一次带朋友回家！
Welcome! Come on in!
欢迎你们 快进来吧！
Komi's mom? Sister?
您是古见同学的妈妈？还是姐姐？
Unrelated?!
不会是外人吧？
It's a pleasure to meet you!
各位好 很高兴认识你们
I'm Shoko's mother, Shuko Komi.
我是硝子的母亲 我叫古见秀子
Forever seventeen!
是永远的17岁哟！
-SPARKLE -FRANTIC WAVING
（闪亮 惊慌挥手）
Darling! Shosuke! Shoko brought friends over!
老公！笑介！ 硝子她带朋友回来了！
Oh, they're not home yet. Silly me.
对了 他还没回家呢
BONK
（敲头）
Wow! Komi's room!
是古见同学的房间！
Hey, Tadano. It smells so good! Snork-snork!
只野同学 好香的味道 快闻！
-Stop that. -Can I sit here?
-不要这样 -我可以坐在床上吗？
ALREADY SITTING
（已经坐上去了）
Oh, a plush cat! So cute!
猫咪布偶好可爱
-Oh, yeah. -AVOIDING THE TOPIC OF HER MOM.
-真的 -（刻意不提到她妈妈的话题）
Hey Tadano, say something!
只野同学 你说点什么啊
DOESN'T KNOW HOW TO BE A HOST
-（不知道该怎么招待客人） -那 那个
Hello! I brought tea and snacks.
来 茶跟点心来了！
Our savior!
救星来了！
Can I use the restroom?
我可以借个厕所吗？
Out and to the right, okay.
出去右转是吧？好
Or so they think!
假装去上厕所
Time to watch Komi and Tadano!
然后偷偷观察古见同学和只野同学！
A boy and girl in a small room!
孤男寡女共处小房间中！
Cue the goofy awkwardness!
快点表现出可笑又尴尬的样子吧！
Hide and seek?
是在玩捉迷藏吗？
5 MINUTES PASS
（5分钟后）
10 MINUTES PASS
（10分钟后）
15 MINUTES PASS
（15分钟后）
Don't you guys ever feel awkward together?
你们两个为什么都不会觉得尴尬呢？
Did you have a stomachache?
驯染 你肚子还好吗？
-That was a lie. -A lie?
-那是骗你们的啦 -骗人的？
My plan failed. Oh well.
计划失败 没办法
But!
但是！
This is Komi's room!
这里是古见同学的房间
Komi is only human.
她终究也是人
There must be something that she doesn't want us to see.
这房间里一定有些 她不想让人看到的东西
That's what I want to see!
我想看的就是这个！
It'll be hilarious!
因为这样才有意思！
Spilling secrets is how friends get close, right?
要曝露秘密才能增进彼此友谊啊！
Having terrible ideas again I see.
这家伙又在动歪脑筋了
Anyway…
话说回来…
The classic teen boy hiding spot…
总不会藏在这种 一般男中学生会藏东西的地方吧
-PAUSE -PANICS
（停住 惊慌）
CONVERSATION TECHNIQUES TALKING TO CATS
（《猴子也会的谈话技巧》 《和猫咪对话》）
Is that your photo album?
那个莫非是你的相簿？
Can we see?
可以看看吗？
-NOD -EMACIATED
（脸色憔悴 点头）
You're so cute!
好可爱！
Where was this? It's so nice!
这是哪里啊？好漂亮！
Komi in a bathing suit!
古见同学的泳装照
FRANTIC WAVING
（惊慌挥手）
Wow, you can play the piano.
原来你还会弹钢琴啊
You've taken a lot of lessons.
你学过好多才艺课呢
So that's why your handwriting is so good.
难怪你写得一手好字
What's this?
这是…
Komi can't converse in English either.
古见同学也无法用英文与人交谈
Sorry, Komi. We stayed so late.
抱歉啊 古见同学 叨扰这么久
Sorry we didn't help clean up.
不好意思 结果都留给你收拾
Thanks for having us.
打扰了
See you tomorrow, Komi.
明天见 古见同学
Bye!
拜拜！
CONVERSATION TECHNIQUES RULES FOR COMMUNICATION
（《传达方式的法则》 《猴子也会的谈话技巧》）
DING
（消息铃声）
ONE NEW MESSAGE
（有一条新消息）
SUBJECT: THANKS!
（标题 谢谢你！）
Hey!
请看！
I secretly took this shot!
其实我偷偷拍下来了
I know you didn't notice at all!
你完全没发现吧？
I won't send it to Tadano!
我不会发给只野同学！
A new picture frame?
你要新相框吗？
It's so rare for you to ask for something.
硝子居然会主动要东西 好难得啊
AFTER SCHOOL
（放学后）
-I WANT TO TRY GOING OUT FOR RAMEN. -Ramen?
-（我想去拉面店） -拉面店？
NOD
（点头）
Yeah! I'm hungry, too.
好啊 刚好我也饿了！
Want to try the place by the station?
我们就去车站前的拉面店吧
It's so unlike you to say you want to go somewhere.
真难得 你居然会主动提出想去哪里
-IT'S MY DREAM TO GO TO A RAMEN SHOP. -You have some odd dreams, Komi.
-（去拉面店是我的梦想） -好奇特的梦想啊 古见同学
Are you all going for ramen?
各位要去拉面店吗？
That's my cue.
那就该轮到我上场了
AGARI IS A RAMEN EXPERT
（上理同学是拉面专家）
A-Agari?
上理同学？
RAMEN DARO
（拉面大郎）
Ta-da! I recommend this place, Ramen Daro!
请看！这就是我推荐的店 拉面大郎
It's famous, isn't it? Daro-style or something.
这间店很有名呢 甚至还有“大郎派”这种说法
-Yeah! -Will it be okay?
-没错！ -但是你没问题吗？
I heard it's greasy and filling.
拉面很油的 而且量又大
LET'S GO.
（我们进去吧）
Quick reply!
马上就回答了！
Yes, it's known for being rich and heavy.
是啊 的确给人油腻、量又大的印象
-Too much for most people. Men go alone. -Agari…?!
-通常都认为是男生一个人来吃… -上理同学？
Oh! I-I-I'm sorry.
啊 对不起！
When it comes to food, I always talk too much.
我一讲到吃的就会停不下来！
I-I see…
这样啊
Oh good, back to the old Agari.
太好了 变回原来的上理同学了
LARGE DOUBLE PORK
（大碗双份猪肉）
Places like this have special rules, right?
这类的店不都会有些自家的规矩吗？
I saw it on TV.
我有在电视上看过
I'll get the same as Agari.
我也点跟你一样的好了
Guilty.
有罪
Uh, guil… huh?
什么“有罪”？什么意思？
Ramen Daro First Commandment…
拉面大郎铁则第一项…
Thou shalt not talk.
店内不准交谈
KOMI'S DOING FINE.
（古见同学游刃有余）
Second commandment.
第二项
-Thou shalt order promptly and sit. -I'm s-sorry!
-必须立即购票 立即就座 -对不起！
Third commandment.
第三项
Thou shalt be polite to the boss and wait calmly.
必须对老板恭敬有礼 一心不乱 静静等候
DOOM
（压迫感）
FWIP
（甩面）
So this is the classic tough-guy ramen boss.
这就是所谓的拉面店超硬派老板吗？
Toppings?
配菜呢？
His voice is tiny!
好小声！
Veggies. Garlic. Lots of lard. Soy sauce.
蔬菜、大蒜、猪油多一点 口味偏咸
A hex?
这什么咒语？
And for the lady?
这位小姐呢？
What will Komi do?
古见同学 怎么办？
NOD
（点头）
He got it!
他居然懂了！
THUD
（魄力惊人）
Wow!
天啊！
This is a lot.
这也太多了吧
Let's eat!
那我开动了！
GLISTEN
（闪亮）
Boss?
老板？
Whoa…
哇！
WORRIED THAT SHE DID SOMETHING WRONG.
（古见同学担心自己是否举止怪异）
Ramen Daro Fourth Commandment…
拉面大郎铁则第四项…
Thou shalt clear your bowl and leave quickly after eating.
吃完了必须立刻归还餐具 马上离席让座
Soggy noodles…
面都坨了
Yeah! That was great!
吃完了 感谢招待！
Wasn't that great?
很好吃吧？
Yeah, but I'm way too full.
是啊 可是实在太饱了
LET'S GO AGAIN SOMETIME.
（下次再去吃吧）
Nah, I think I'm good.
不 我还是算了
But they started craving it,
但不知为何吃上瘾了
and they went again a week later.
一星期后又去吃了
MISSION 15 "IT'S JUST A BLOOD PACT."
（任务15 血之契约）
You didn't see it yesterday?
你昨天没看吗？
No, I didn't.
没看
-It was really good. -Oh yeah?
-超有趣的 -真的吗？
-You missed out. -Seriously?
-不看是你人生的损失 -哪有那么夸张
PASS
（快步通过）
So there are four types of wrappers that tell a little story.
然后外包装有四种款式 整个构成一个故事
Two don't even have rice crackers in the picture.
当中有两种上面 根本没在吃煎饼 也没画出来
Like, why is there an old lady? They used to be grilled too.
首次买的人会想说怎么会有老奶奶 虽然以前都在烤煎饼
Beetles have average brains, even though they're mammals.
听说独角仙的脑袋是普通大小 虽说仓鼠是哺乳类…
-COLLAPSE -SHOCK
（惊吓 倒下）
W-What can this be?
这是怎么回事？
The forbidden power within me, Dragon Force, is tingling!
我体内的禁忌之力 龙之力竟产生了反应？
But why?
为什么会这样？
JOLT
（惊吓）
Is that you, Princess Komilia?
难道是古见莉亚公主？
Princess Komilia?
古见莉亚公主？
Nakanaka has a rich fantasy life.
中中同学有中二病
Komi, do you know Nakanaka?
古见同学 你认识她吗？
HAS NO IDEA
（没印象）
Princess Komilia, did you forget me?
古见莉亚公主 你忘了吗？
It's me!
是我啊！
My real name is Marsault Les Primavera!
我的真名是 玛路斯特蕾丝普利玛贝拉！
Real name?
真名？
REAL NAME OMOHARU NAKANAKA
（本名 中中思春）
I understand.
也不能怪你
We have died and been reborn many times since then, across nations.
毕竟我们已经历数次轮回转世 甚至都已超越了世界线
-FORMER FANTISIZER. -Something here feels familiar…
-（他以前也是中二病） -等等 这感觉好熟悉
Princess Komilia!
古见莉亚公主！
If our Dragon Forces are over 10m apart, it will cause a huge explosion.
我俩的龙之力只要相距 超过十米就会引发大爆炸
And um, the world will be destroyed!
那个 世界就会毁灭！
H-Hurry and make a blood pact with me!
快点和我订下血之契约吧！
It was alright until now though?
可是之前都没事 不是吗？
TELL ME MORE.
（请告诉我大爆炸的详情）
She believed it.
她相信了
Um, when my Dragon Force tingles,
也就是说龙之力一旦产生反应
it, uh, causes a resonance.
就会引发共振…
WHAT IS THE DRAGON FORCE?
（什么是“龙之力”？）
It ruins the effect when you have to explain.
要说明这种事是很难为情的
The premise doesn't matter!
不要管这些细节设定了！
Hurry! We must form a blood pact!
快点和我订下血之契约吧！
She said "premise."
她脱口说出这是“设定”了
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
My evil eye is out of control!
我的邪眼失控了！
EVIL EYE = PINKEYE
（邪眼就是指麦粒肿）
I've got to go to the nurse's office!
我要赶紧去保健室！
I think blood pact means she wants to be your friend.
她说的“血之契约” 该不会是想和你做朋友吧？
Was Nakanaka always that cringey?
中中的中二病有这么严重吗？
She's like how Tadano used to be.
感觉好像以前的只野同学
WHAT DO YOU MEAN?
（什么是“中二病”？）
Oh uh.
那个啊 就是…
Hey, Najimi!
驯染 慢着！
Back in junior high…
所谓的“中二病”就是…
They call me Hitohito Tadano.
我的名字叫只野仁人
Second year, junior high.
是初中二年级学生
As you can see,
看也知道
I'm kind of a big deal.
我绝非凡人
-POSING -THINKS HE'S A BIG DEAL
（说话看着镜头 脑中称自己绝非凡人）
-And then… -Yeah?
-所以… -怎样？
That girl…
那个女孩啊…
That's Kawai, the prettiest girl in class.
那是本班的班花河合同学
Good morning, Tadano!
早安 只野同学
Najimi. It's on.
驯染 今天要执行“那个”
What's on?
哪个？
Operation L. We're doing it.
准备进行L作战
EVERYTHING'S AN "OPERATION"
（很爱说“某某作战”）
The "L" in Operation L is…
L作战的“L”代表…
H-Hey Kawai.
嗨 河合同学
I think you see how I feel, bruh.
你明白我的心意了哟？
CLASSIC CRINGE #4 "BRUH"
（中二病症状四 “哟”）
Listen! I've been into you since--
我一直都很喜欢你…
Sorry.
抱歉
Huh? Why?
什么？为什么？
You're just kinda cringey.
因为你太中二了
It's not cool.
很丢人
I'm never going to play it cool again.
我以后再也不装了
I'll be normal.
就平平凡凡地
Just normal.
当个平凡人
I won't make waves.
过平静安详的生活吧
Tadano's personality was cemented.
只野同学的人格就此成形
Like that.
大概就像这样
It's this phase where kids think they're special.
“中二病”指的就是 青春期时自命不凡的症状
They have a rich fantasy life. Tadano, you were so cringey.
只野同学当时的中二病可精彩了
Huh? Tadano?
奇怪 只野同学？
-A part of him died! -HAUNTED BY THE PAST.
-他已经死了 -（不堪的过去被揭穿 心已死）
Alright. We'll do some warmup stretches.
好 那准备做热身运动
Make groups of two.
你们随意去找搭档
Pairs.
两个人一组
Ko…
古…
Komi!
古见同学！
Komi, be my partner!
古见同学 跟我一组
Pick me, Komi! We're friends, right?
选我吧 古见同学 我们不是朋友吗？
-Komi, me! -Partner with me!
-古见同学 选我！ -跟我一组！
-Let's do it! -Uh…
-我们一组吧！ -好啊
-I'm so stiff today. -Oh yeah?
-我今天肌肉酸痛 -是吗？
Fools, all of them.
有什么可嚣张的
They're not of darkness, like me.
他们和我这暗黑一族 终究不是同一类的人
I can't blame them.
也难怪
If any ordinary souls touched my Dragon Force,
常人要是碰触到我的龙之力
their bodies would melt to the ground.
那可是会全身溃烂的
Why won't anyone…
为什么…
pair up with me…
都没人想和我一组？
You startled me!
吓死我了！
You'll stretch with me?
你愿意和我一起做热身操吗？
-Aw, lucky. -I'm jealous!
-真好！ -真羡慕！
I wanted to do that.
好想跟她一起做那个动作
Waah. Why didn't she choose me?
可恶 为什么没有选我啦？古见同学
Time for volleyball.
接下来要打排球
Okay!
好！
Komi!
古见同学！
Um.
那个…
Th-Thank…
谢谢…
I tricked you, Princess Komilia!
你这笨蛋被我骗了 古见莉亚公主！
I'm not your servant, Marsault Les Whatever.
我并不是你的仆人 那个玛路斯特蕾丝某某！
I'm Lord Malt Trie Vessner, of the Dark Dragon!
我乃暗黑龙人玛尔托多利维斯纳卿！
Through our blood pact, you are now my vassal!
你已和我订下血之契约 从此你就是我的仆人了！
Well, I suppose I can pardon you…
算了 你不当我的仆人也无所谓
Komi made a blood pact with Nakanaka.
古见同学和中中同学 订下了血之契约
CLASS PRESIDENT
（班长）
CLASS VICE PRESIDENT
（副班长）
I WAS READING IN THE LIBRARY AND NOW LOOK AT THE TIME.
（我在图书室看书 不知不觉就这么晚了）
NOD
（点头）
TADANO, I HAVE YOUR UMBRELLA. SIGNED, A THIEF NAMED "N".
（只野同学的伞由我收下了 怪盗“N”）
GRAZE
（轻轻碰到）
Once exams are over it'll be summer break.
考试完了之后就是暑假了
We got so much homework. It's going to be tough.
暑假作业还挺多的 得加把劲才行
What's wrong, Komi?
你怎么了？古见同学
I bought an umbrella.
我买了一把伞
Oh, here's a towel.
这是毛巾
It was a three-pack. Have one.
一包有三条 别客气 拿去用吧
If I'm wrong, I apologize.
如果是我误会了 我道歉
Did you read that note from Najimi and wait for me by the shoe lockers?
你该不会是看了驯染的字条 才在鞋柜那里等我吧？
The sun came out.
放晴了
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：薛卓